PREFACE The artist is the creator of beautiful things. To reveal art and
conceal the artist is art’s aim. The critic is he who can translate into
another manner or a new material his impression of beautiful
things. The highest as the lowest form of criticism is a mode of
autobiography. Those who find ugly meanings in beautiful things are corrupt
without being charming. This is a fault.
Those who find beautiful meanings in beautiful things are the cultivated. For
these there is hope. They are the elect to whom beautiful things mean only
beauty. There is no such thing as a moral or an immoral book. Books are well
written, or badly written. That is all.
The 19th century dislike of realism is the rage of Caliban seeing his own face in a
glass. The 19th century dislike of romanticism is the rage of Caliban not
seeing his own face in a glass. The moral life of man forms part
of the subject matter of the artist, but the morality of art consists
in the perfect use of an imperfect medium. No artist desires to prove
anything. Even things that are true can be proved. No artist has ethical
sympathies. An ethical sympathy in an artist is an unpardonable mannerism of
style. No artist is ever morbid. The artist can express everything. Thought
and language are to the artist instruments of an art. Vice and virtue
are to the artist materials for an art.
From the point of view of form, the type of all the arts is the art of the
musician. From the point of view of feeling, the actor’s craft is the the
type. All art is at once surface and symbol. Those who go beneath the surface
do so at their peril. Those who read the symbol do so at their peril. It is the
spectator, and not life, that art really mirrors. Diversity of opinion about a
work of art shows that the work is new, complex, and vital. When critics disagree,
the artist is in accord with himself. We can forgive a man for making a useful
thing as long as he does not admire it. The only excuse for making a useless
thing is that one admires it intensely.
All art is quite useless. OSCAR